Let's explore ways of fixing some common issues in data.
我们来看一些常见数据问题的解决方式
Here's a toy data set I created for this lesson.
这是我为本课程创建的一个小型数据集
It has 11 instances of
其中有 11 项用户产品互动记录
user product interactions recording whether the user liked the product,
记录了用户是否喜爱产品 (liked 字段)
how long they viewed the product,
浏览产品的时长 (view_duration 字段)
whether it was on a website or through a mobile app,
是通过网站浏览还是移动应用浏览 (source 字段)
and what time they started viewing the product.
又是在何时开始浏览的 (timestamp 字段)
Pause the video and see if you can spot any potential issues in this data.
暂停本视频 试试看你能否找出这批数据的潜在问题
Let's adjust three issues in this data set that are quite common in the real world.
我们来处理这个数据集里的三个问题 这些问题在现实中很常见
The first one is missing data which we find in the view_duration column.
第一个是缺失数据 问题出现在 view_duration 一列中
There are a total of 11 entries or rows in this data set,
这个数据集总共录入了 11 条数据 也就是 11 行
but only 8 non-null values in view_duration.
可 view_duration 一列仅有 8 个非空值 (non-null)
That means, there are three null values which we can also see here.
这也就意味着有三个空值 大家从这里也可以看出来
This is a small toy data set,
这只是个小型数据集
so we're able to see all the null values here.
所以我们能在这看到所有空值
But normally, you check these values for bigger data sets.
但是通常在更大的数据集中 你得在这里进行空值检查
The second issue we'll address is duplicates which we find in rows three and four.
我们要处理的第二个问题是冗余 可参见第三和第四行
Again, we only notice this here because this is a small toy data set.
还是那个道理 现在我们之所以能发现这个问题 只是因为这是一个小型数据集
I'll show you a better way to check for duplicates in a little bit.
等下我会教你一个更好的办法来查找冗余数据
The third issue we'll tackle is incorrect data types.
第三个要解决的问题是数据类型错误
Here, timestamp is represented as a string when ideally,
这里的 timestamp (时间戳) 为字符串
it should be represented as a datetime object.
可理想情况下 timestamp 应为 datetime 对象
Remember, it says object instead of string here because
记住 这里显示为 object 而不是 string
pandas' stores pointers through strings instead of the strings themselves.
是因为 pandas 存储的是字符串的指针 而不是字符串本身
Okay, so let's start with the first problem, missing data.
现在我们从第一个问题开始解决 也就是数据缺失
Missing data is an issue that should be handled differently depending on
数据缺失要如何处理 取决于不同的因素
several factors such as the reason those values
如值缺失的原因
are missing and whether the occurrences seem random.
缺失是否为随机情况等
One way of handling them is imputing them with the mean.
处理办法之一是用平均值填充缺失值
You can do this quickly and efficiently with a convenient function from pandas.
pandas 里有个很方便的函数 能让你快捷高效地完成这一操作
First, let's get the mean of the view_duration column.
首先 我们要取得 view_duration 一列的平均值
Now, let's use pandas' fillna function to fill null values with this mean.
然后 用 pandas 的 fillna 函数把平均值填充到各空值处
Take a look at the data frame now.
看看现在的 DataFrame
Did this fix the problem?
问题解决了吗？
Instead of making changes to the original column,
函数并没有修改原来的列
it actually just returned a new column with the changes which we didn't store anywhere.
只是把更改返回成一个新列 这一列并没有储存到任何地方
To keep the changes,
为了保存更改
make sure to assign it to the original like this.
要记住像这样把更改赋值到原来的列里
Alternatively, you can use a parameter called
你也可以用一个叫 inplace 的参数
inplace to make the changes, well, in place.
来实现“原地”更改
Awesome. We just fixed our missing data issue.
好极了 数据缺失问题解决了
Next, let's deal with the problem of duplicate data.
接下来要处理的是数据冗余问题
There are multiple reasons you may end up with duplicated data,
导致数据冗余的原因有很多
like combined data sources, or human error.
比如数据源合并或人为过失
This is a simple scenario where two rows,
这个情景里问题很简单 只有两行
three and four, are identical.
也就是第三和第四行相同
This toy data set is small enough for us to count visually.
这个小型数据集很小 看一眼都能数出来
For bigger data sets,
但对于大型数据集
you can use the duplicated function to see which rows are duplicates.
你可以用 duplicated 函数来查看冗余行有哪些
By default, this marks duplicates as True excluding the first instance.
该函数默认将非首次出现的冗余行标为 True
And it considers a row to be a duplicate only if the values in all the columns match.
除非行中每列的值都相同 不然该行不会被视为冗余
You can change both of these with different parameters.
你可以用不同的参数更改这两个默认设置
For larger data sets,
对于大些的数据集
it would probably be more helpful to get
有个办法可能更有帮助
a count of the duplicates in the data set like this.
那就是像这样计算数据集数据冗余的数量
To drop duplicates, we can use pandas' drop_duplicates function.
要删除冗余值 我们可以用 pandas 的 drop_duplicates 函数
Again, we have to use the inplace parameter or assign
和之前一样 使用该函数时 我们也要用 inplace 参数
the output to the original data frame when using this function.
或手动把输出结果赋值到原始 DataFrame 中
You can see, we've dropped row four,
正如你看到的 我们删掉了第四行
the row marked as a duplicate.
也就是标为冗余的那行
Now, this was a simple situation where the entire row was identical.
不过这个情景很简单 整行数据都一样
You can imagine duplicated data scenarios that are a bit more complicated.
你可以想象那些较为复杂的数据冗余情景
For example, let's say we had data on patients from a hospital.
比如 假设我们手里有一家医院的患者数据
What happens when you come across two rows with the same patient
如果你看到两行数据有相同的患者 ID
ID but different data on medical exam results? Do you combine them?
却记录着不同的体检结果 那怎么办？ 是要把两行数据合并起来呢？
Only keep the latest one?
还是保留最新的那一行？
This is a situation you'd have to investigate more.
这时候你就得调查更多信息了
For this scenario, you'd likely identify
在这个情景中 你可能要只根据患者 ID 列
duplicates only based on the column recording the patient ID.
来判断冗余与否
You can use a subset parameter in the duplicated and drop_duplicate functions to do this.
你可以在 duplicated 和 drop_duplicate 函数中使用 subset 参数
Finally, let's address the last issue, incorrect data types.
最后 我们来解决第三个问题 数据类型错误
Incorrect data types is also a problem data analysts frequently come across.
错误的数据类型也是数据分析师频频遇到的问题
In this case, timestamps are represented as strings instead of datetimes.
在这里 时间戳以字符串类型呈现 而不是 datetime 类型
This isn't a critical issue but datetimes are much more convenient to work with.
这虽然不是什么大问题 但如果你想更轻松地从中提取具体信息
If you want to extract specific information from them or filter them more easily.
或对其进行过滤的话 datetime 型处理起来会更方便
Let's use the pandas function to_datetime to convert this column to datetime.
我们来使用 pandas 的 to_datetime 函数 将本列转换为 datetime 型
Now, we can see timestamp is represented as a datetime.
现在我们可以看到 timestamp 已经是 datetime 型了
By the way, even if you save this to a CSV file after making this change,
顺便说一句 完成修改后 就算你把更改保存到 CSV 文件里
it will still be read as a string by default the next time you open it.
下次打开 文件仍会默认将数据读为字符串类型
You'd have to convert it again after opening
所以下次打开 CSV 文件 你还是得再转一次类型
the CSV file or use parameters like parsedates in the read_csv function.
或者在 read_csv 函数中使用诸如 parsedates 之类的参数
Although, if the strings you have to parse are formatted unconventionally,
不过 如果你要解析的字符串是非常规的格式
the function to_datetime provides more options than the parameters in read_csv.
那么用 to_datetime 函数比用 read_csv 函数的参数选择面更大些